Earth.
Earth
is
the
third
planet
from
the
Sun
and
the
only
astronomical
object
known
to
harbor
life.
This
is
made
possible
by
Earth
being
an
ocean
world,
the
only
one
in
the
Solar
System
sustaining
liquid
surface
water.
Almost
all
of
Earth's
water
is
contained
in
its
global
ocean,
covering
seventy
point
eight
percent
of
Earth's
crust.
The
remaining
twenty
nine
point
two
percent
of
Earth's
crust
is
land,
most
of
which
is
located
in
the
form
of
continental
landmasses
within
Earth's
land
hemisphere.
Most
of
Earth's
land
is
at
least
somewhat
humid
and
covered
by
vegetation,
while
large
ice
sheets
at
Earth's
polar
deserts
retain
more
water
than
Earth's
groundwater,
lakes,
rivers,
and
atmospheric
water
combined.
Earth's
crust
consists
of
slowly
moving
tectonic
plates,
which
interact
to
produce
mountain
ranges,
volcanoes,
and
earthquakes.
Earth
has
a
liquid
outer
core
that
generates
a
magnetosphere
capable
of
deflecting
most
of
the
destructive
solar
winds
and
cosmic
radiation.
Earth
has
a
dynamic
atmosphere,
which
sustains
Earth's
surface
conditions
and
protects
it
from
most
meteoroids
and
UV-light
at
entry.
It
is
composed
primarily
of
nitrogen
and
oxygen.
Water
vapor
is
widely
present
in
the
atmosphere,
forming
clouds
that
cover
most
of
the
planet.
The
water
vapor
acts
as
a
greenhouse
gas
and,
together
with
other
greenhouse
gases
in
the
atmosphere,
particularly
carbon
dioxide
(CO
two),
creates
the
conditions
for
both
liquid
surface
water
and
vapor
to
persist
via
the
capturing
of
energy
from
the
Sun's
light.
This
process
maintains
the
current
average
surface
temperature
of
fourteen
point
seven
six
degrees
Celsius
(fifty
eight
point
five
seven
degrees
Fahrenheit),
at
which
water
is
liquid
under
normal
atmospheric
pressure.
Differences
in
the
amount
of
captured
energy
between
geographic
regions
(as
with
the
equatorial
region
receiving
more
sunlight
than
the
polar
regions)
drive
atmospheric
and
ocean
currents,
producing
a
global
climate
system
with
different
climate
regions,
and
a
range
of
weather
phenomena
such
as
precipitation,
allowing
components
such
as
carbon
and
nitrogen
to
cycle.
Earth
is
rounded
into
an
ellipsoid
with
a
circumference
of
about
forty
thousand
kilometres
(twenty
four
thousand
nine
hundred
miles).
It
is
the
densest
planet
in
the
Solar
System.
Of
the
four
rocky
planets,
it
is
the
largest
and
most
massive.
Earth
is
about
eight
light-minutes
(one
AU)
away
from
the
Sun
and
orbits
it,
taking
a
year
(about
three
hundred
sixty
five
point
two
five
days)
to
complete
one
revolution.
Earth
rotates
around
its
own
axis
in
slightly
less
than
a
day
(in
about
twenty
three
hours
and
fifty
six
minutes).
Earth's
axis
of
rotation
is
tilted
with
respect
to
the
perpendicular
to
its
orbital
plane
around
the
Sun,
producing
seasons.
Earth
is
orbited
by
one
permanent
natural
satellite,
the
Moon,
which
orbits
Earth
at
three
hundred
eighty
four
thousand
hundred
kilometers
(two
hundred
thirty
eight
thousand
hundred
fifty
five
miles)—
one
point
two
eight
light
seconds—and
is
roughly
a
quarter
as
wide
Earth.
The
Moon's
gravity
helps
stabilize
Earth's
axis,
causes
tides
and
gradually
slows
Earth's
rotation.
Likewise,
Earth's
gravitational
pull
has
already
made
the
Moon's
rotation
tidally
locked,
keeping
the
same
near
side
facing
Earth.
Earth,
like
most
other
bodies
in
the
Solar
System,
formed
about
four
point
five
billion
years
ago
from
gas
and
dust
in
the
early
Solar
System.
The
formation
of
the
ocean
and
the
subsequent
development
of
life
occurred
during
the
first
billion
years
of
Earth's
history.
Life
spread
globally
and
has
been
altering
Earth's
atmosphere
and
surface,
leading
to
the
Great
Oxidation
Event
two
billion
years
ago.
Humans
emerged
three
hundred
thousand
years
ago
in
Africa
and
have
spread
across
every
continent
on
Earth.
Humans
depend
on
Earth's
biosphere
and
natural
resources
for
their
survival,
but
have
increasingly
impacted
the
planet's
environment.
Humanity's
current
impact
on
Earth's
climate
and
biosphere
is
unsustainable,
threatening
the
livelihood
of
humans
and
many
other
forms
of
life,
and
causing
widespread
extinctions.